<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
        "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<!--
  NOTE:  This XML file is input used to produce the authoritative copy of an
  OpenID Foundation specification.  The authoritative copy is the HTML output.
  This XML source file is not authoritative.  The statement ipr="none" is
  present only to satisfy the document compilation tool and is not indicative
  of the IPR status of this specification.  The IPR for this specification is
  described in the "Notices" section.  This is a public document and not a
  private document, as the private="..." declaration could be taken to indicate.
-->
<rfc category="std" docName="openid-cross-federation-trust-marks-1_0" ipr="none"
     submissionType="IETF" consensus="true"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="5" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc private="Draft 0.1" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Cross-Federation Trust Marks">Cross-Federation Trust via OpenID Federation Trust Marks</title>

    <!-- TODO: complete author details before publication. -->
    <author fullname="Niels" initials="N." role="editor" surname="(editor)">
      <organization>Sphereon</organization>
      <address>
        <email>editor@example.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="19" month="June" year="2026"/>

    <workgroup>Independent Draft</workgroup>

    <keyword>OpenID</keyword>
    <keyword>OpenID Federation</keyword>
    <keyword>Trust Mark</keyword>
    <keyword>Trust Anchor</keyword>
    <keyword>Verifiable Credential</keyword>
    <keyword>Cross-Federation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        OpenID Federation 1.1 establishes trust between two Entities by
        resolving a Trust Chain to a common Trust Anchor. This requirement
        prevents a Relying Party in one federation from trusting an Entity whose
        Entity Statements are anchored only in a different federation, unless a
        common superior Trust Anchor or out-of-band cross-configuration exists.
      </t>
      <t>
        This profile defines how a Trust Mark issued within an Accrediting
        Federation can carry the information needed for a Relying Party in that
        federation to establish trust in a Credential Issuer anchored in a
        separate Subject Federation, without a shared Trust Anchor and without
        pre-configuring the Subject Federation's Trust Anchor. It further defines
        how such a Trust Mark is bound to the Verifiable Credentials issued by
        that Credential Issuer using the W3C Verifiable Credentials Data Model.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        In a typical OpenID Federation deployment a Relying Party trusts one or
        more Trust Anchors that are configured out of band. An Entity is trusted
        when a valid Trust Chain can be resolved from that Entity to one of those
        configured Trust Anchors (<xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section
        10). Trust Marks (Section 7) are evaluated separately: a Trust Mark is a
        signed JWT asserting that its subject conforms to a set of criteria
        defined by an accreditation authority, and a Relying Party trusts a Trust
        Mark when the Trust Mark Issuer is recognized for that Trust Mark type by
        a Trust Anchor the Relying Party uses.
      </t>
      <t>
        This profile addresses the case in which the accreditation and the
        accredited Entity live in different federations:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>The Credential Issuer is a Leaf Entity whose Entity Statements are
          anchored in the Subject Federation.</t>
          <t>The accreditation is expressed as a Trust Mark issued by a Trust
          Mark Issuer recognized in the Accrediting Federation.</t>
          <t>A Relying Party that trusts the Accrediting Federation's Trust
          Anchor needs to trust the accreditation and to verify the authenticity
          of the Credential Issuer and its issued Credentials, even though it
          does not natively trust the Subject Federation's Trust Anchor.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The mechanism is to convey, inside the Trust Mark, the identity and keys
        of the Subject Federation's Trust Anchor, so the Relying Party can
        resolve and validate the Credential Issuer's Trust Chain on the basis of
        a Trust Mark it already trusts.
      </t>

      <section anchor="requirements-language" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
          14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
          when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
        <t>
          This profile uses the terms defined in <xref
          target="OpenID.Federation"/>. Unless otherwise stated, all
          base-specification processing rules continue to apply; this profile
          only adds requirements.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>
          This profile defines the following terms in addition to those of <xref
          target="OpenID.Federation"/>.
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Accrediting Federation (AF):">The federation whose Trust
            Anchor recognizes the Trust Mark Issuer for the Trust Mark type
            defined by a deployment of this profile, via the
            <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_issuers</spanx> Claim.</t>
            <t hangText="Subject Federation (SF):">The federation in which the
            Credential Issuer is a Leaf Entity and whose Trust Anchor is
            authoritative for that Credential Issuer's Entity Statements.</t>
            <t hangText="Subject Trust Anchor:">The Trust Anchor of the Subject
            Federation, at which the Credential Issuer's Trust Chain
            terminates.</t>
            <t hangText="Credential Issuer (CI):">The Entity that issues
            Verifiable Credentials and that is the <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>
            of the Trust Mark. The Credential Issuer is a Leaf Entity in the
            Subject Federation.</t>
            <t hangText="Trust Mark Issuer (TMI):">The accreditation authority
            that issues the Trust Mark, recognized in the Accrediting Federation.
            Defined in <xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>.</t>
            <t hangText="Relying Party (RP):">The party consuming the Verifiable
            Credential (the Verifier), which trusts the Accrediting Federation's
            Trust Anchor.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The Accrediting Federation and the Subject Federation MAY be operated
          by different organizations and MUST NOT be assumed to share a Trust
          Anchor.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="relationship" title="Relationship to OpenID Federation 1.1">
        <t>
          This document is a profile (extension) of <xref
          target="OpenID.Federation"/>. It defines additional Claims that appear
          within Trust Mark JWTs (Section 7.1 of the base specification permits
          additional members), additional Relying Party processing rules, and a
          binding of Trust Marks to Verifiable Credentials. It introduces no
          changes to Entity Statement, Trust Chain, or Federation Endpoint
          processing.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="architecture" title="Architecture">
      <t>
        An Entity acting under this profile participates in two distinct and
        orthogonal trust relationships:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Accreditation recognition (Accrediting Federation). The Relying
          Party trusts the Trust Mark because the Trust Mark Issuer is recognized
          by the AF Trust Anchor for the relevant Trust Mark type. This is the
          standard Trust Mark trust model of <xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>,
          Section 7.</t>
          <t>Credential Issuer authenticity (Subject Federation). The Relying
          Party establishes the Credential Issuer's keys and metadata by
          resolving a Trust Chain that terminates at the Subject Trust Anchor.
          The Relying Party learns to trust the Subject Trust Anchor from the
          Trust Mark, which pins that Trust Anchor's identity and keys.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        These two relationships meet only at the Relying Party. The Trust Mark
        Issuer's own Trust Chain MUST resolve to a Trust Anchor the Relying Party
        trusts (the AF Trust Anchor); the Credential Issuer's Trust Chain
        resolves to the Subject Trust Anchor pinned in the Trust Mark.
      </t>
      <t>
        The recognition of the Trust Mark Issuer cannot itself be bootstrapped
        from the Trust Mark, because that recognition is the root of the Relying
        Party's trust in the accreditation. Consequently, this profile pins only
        the Subject Trust Anchor inside the Trust Mark; the Trust Mark Issuer MUST
        be recognized natively in the Accrediting Federation (<xref
        target="trust-domains"/>).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="tm-type" title="Trust Mark Type">
      <t>
        A deployment of this profile MUST define one Trust Mark type identifier,
        owned by the Accrediting Federation. The Trust Mark type identifier is a
        URL, collision-resistant across federations, and SHOULD be constructed
        from a URL that uniquely identifies the Accrediting Federation or trust
        framework.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Trust Mark Definition referenced by the Trust Mark <spanx
        style="verb">ref</spanx> Claim MUST specify, at minimum: the accreditation
        criteria; the set of credential types in scope; any additional matching
        constraints (<xref target="accredited-credentials"/>); the renewal and
        revocation process; and the Trust Chain Constraints (<xref
        target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 6.2) that a Relying Party MUST apply
        to the Credential Issuer's Trust Chain (<xref target="rp-processing"/>,
        step 6).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="tm-profile" title="Trust Mark Profile">
      <t>
        A Trust Mark conforming to this profile is a JWT with the <spanx
        style="verb">typ</spanx> header parameter <spanx
        style="verb">trust-mark+jwt</spanx> and the Claims defined in <xref
        target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 7.1 (<spanx
        style="verb">iss</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>, <spanx
        style="verb">trust_mark_type</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">iat</spanx>,
        and optionally <spanx style="verb">exp</spanx>, <spanx
        style="verb">ref</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">delegation</spanx>, <spanx
        style="verb">logo_uri</spanx>). In addition, the following Claims are
        defined by this profile.
      </t>

      <section anchor="subject-trust-anchor" title="subject_trust_anchor">
        <t>
          REQUIRED. String. The Entity Identifier of the Subject Trust Anchor,
          i.e. the Trust Anchor at which the Trust Chain for the Entity identified
          by the <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx> Claim MUST terminate. The value
          MUST be an Entity Identifier as defined by <xref
          target="OpenID.Federation"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sta-thumbprints" title="subject_trust_anchor_jwks_thumbprints">
        <t>
          REQUIRED. Array of strings. A non-empty array of JWK SHA-256
          Thumbprints <xref target="RFC7638"/>, base64url-encoded, each
          identifying a Federation Entity Key of the Subject Trust Anchor
          identified by <spanx style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx>.
        </t>
        <t>
          When validating the Credential Issuer's Trust Chain, the Relying Party
          MUST verify that the terminating Trust Anchor publishes at least one
          Federation Entity Key whose thumbprint matches a value in this array,
          and MUST use only such matched key(s) as the trust root for that Trust
          Chain.
        </t>
        <t>
          Thumbprints, rather than a full JWK Set, are pinned so that Subject
          Trust Anchor key rollover does not invalidate outstanding Trust Marks;
          multiple values MAY be present to span a rollover. A deployment that
          requires re-accreditation on Subject Trust Anchor key rollover MAY
          instead pin a single thumbprint.
        </t>
        <t>
          Note: pinning the Subject Trust Anchor's keys (rather than only its
          Entity Identifier) ensures the security of the cross-federation Trust
          Chain reduces to the Trust Mark Issuer's signature, and does not depend
          on transport security at the Subject Trust Anchor's endpoints.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="accredited-credentials" title="accredited_credentials">
        <t>
          REQUIRED. A non-empty JSON array of objects. Each object identifies a
          credential type that the Credential Issuer (<spanx
          style="verb">sub</spanx>) is accredited to issue under this Trust Mark,
          and MAY further constrain the accreditation. Each object has the
          following members:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="format:">REQUIRED. String. The Credential Format
            Identifier (for example, a format identifier registered for OpenID
            for Verifiable Credential Issuance), such as <spanx
            style="verb">ldp_vc</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">jwt_vc_json</spanx>,
            or <spanx style="verb">dc+sd-jwt</spanx>.</t>
            <t hangText="(type identifier):">A credential type identifier
            appropriate to <spanx style="verb">format</spanx>. For W3C Verifiable
            Credentials Data Model formats (e.g. <spanx
            style="verb">ldp_vc</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">jwt_vc_json</spanx>),
            <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> is REQUIRED and is a JSON array of
            strings naming the Credential <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> values,
            other than the base <spanx style="verb">VerifiableCredential</spanx>,
            that scope the accreditation. For IETF SD-JWT VC (<spanx
            style="verb">dc+sd-jwt</spanx>), <spanx style="verb">vct</spanx> is
            REQUIRED and is the string Verifiable Credential Type.</t>
            <t hangText="constraints:">OPTIONAL. A JSON object of additional Claim
            constraints that a presented Verifiable Credential MUST satisfy to be
            considered covered by this accreditation entry (for example, a
            qualification identifier carried as a Credential Claim). The
            interpretation of <spanx style="verb">constraints</spanx> is defined
            by the Trust Mark Definition (<xref target="tm-type"/>).</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          A deployment SHOULD issue one Trust Mark per (Credential Issuer,
          credential type) pair, so that the Trust Mark Status mechanism (<xref
          target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 8.4) can revoke a single
          accreditation independently of others.
        </t>
        <t>
          The credential type identifiers in <spanx
          style="verb">accredited_credentials</spanx> are governed by their
          respective type authorities and are independent of both the Accrediting
          Federation and the Subject Federation.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="delegation" title="Trust Mark Delegation">
      <t>
        Where the Trust Mark Owner and the Trust Mark Issuer are different
        Entities - which is the expected case for this profile, with the
        Accrediting Federation operator owning the Trust Mark type and an
        accreditation authority issuing it - the Trust Mark MUST contain a <spanx
        style="verb">delegation</spanx> Claim as defined in <xref
        target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 7.2, and the AF Trust Anchor MUST
        publish the corresponding <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_owners</spanx>
        entry (<xref target="af-config"/>).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="af-config" title="Accrediting Federation Trust Anchor Configuration">
      <t>
        The Accrediting Federation Trust Anchor MUST recognize the Trust Mark
        Issuer for the profile's Trust Mark type by listing it in the <spanx
        style="verb">trust_mark_issuers</spanx> Claim of its Entity
        Configuration.
      </t>
      <t>
        Where Trust Mark Delegation is used (<xref target="delegation"/>), the AF
        Trust Anchor MUST publish a <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_owners</spanx>
        entry for the Trust Mark type, containing the Owner's Entity Identifier
        (<spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>) and the Owner's signing keys (<spanx
        style="verb">jwks</spanx>).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rp-processing" title="Relying Party Processing">
      <t>
        On receiving a Verifiable Credential whose acceptance is gated on
        accreditation under this profile, the Relying Party MUST perform all of
        the following steps. Failure of any step means the accreditation is not
        established and the Credential MUST NOT be accepted on the basis of this
        profile.
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Obtain the Trust Mark. Obtain the Trust Mark from one of: the
          Credential Issuer's <spanx style="verb">trust_marks</spanx> Claim (<xref
          target="advertisement"/>); the Trust Mark Issuer's Trust Marked Entities
          Listing (<xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 8.5); or the
          Verifiable Credential itself (<xref target="binding"/>). The <spanx
          style="verb">trust_mark_type</spanx> MUST equal the Trust Mark type
          expected by the Relying Party.</t>
          <t>Recognize the Trust Mark Issuer. The Trust Mark <spanx
          style="verb">iss</spanx> MUST appear in the Relying Party's Accrediting
          Federation Trust Anchor <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_issuers</spanx>
          Claim for this <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_type</spanx>. The Relying
          Party MUST resolve and validate a Trust Chain for the Trust Mark Issuer
          to that Trust Anchor (<xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Sections 7.3
          and 10) and obtain the Issuer's Federation Entity Keys.</t>
          <t>Validate delegation. If the Trust Mark contains a <spanx
          style="verb">delegation</spanx> Claim, the Relying Party MUST validate
          it against the <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_owners</spanx> entry for
          this <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_type</spanx> in the AF Trust Anchor,
          per <xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 7.2.</t>
          <t>Verify the Trust Mark. The Relying Party MUST verify the Trust Mark
          signature using the Trust Mark Issuer's Federation Entity Keys, and MUST
          verify <spanx style="verb">iat</spanx> and, if present, <spanx
          style="verb">exp</spanx>.</t>
          <t>Bind subject to issuer. The Trust Mark <spanx
          style="verb">sub</spanx> MUST equal the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx>
          (issuer identifier) of the Verifiable Credential.</t>
          <t>Resolve the Credential Issuer Trust Chain. The Relying Party MUST
          resolve a Trust Chain for the Verifiable Credential's issuer that
          terminates at <spanx style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx>. The
          terminating Trust Anchor MUST publish a Federation Entity Key whose JWK
          SHA-256 Thumbprint matches a value in <spanx
          style="verb">subject_trust_anchor_jwks_thumbprints</spanx>, and that key
          MUST be used as the trust root. The Relying Party MUST apply the Trust
          Chain Constraints specified by the Trust Mark Definition (<xref
          target="tm-type"/>) to this Trust Chain.</t>
          <t>Verify Credential authenticity. The Relying Party MUST verify the
          Verifiable Credential using the issuer keys established by the resolved
          Trust Chain.</t>
          <t>Verify coverage. The Verifiable Credential MUST match at least one
          entry of <spanx style="verb">accredited_credentials</spanx>: its format
          and credential type identifier MUST match, and any <spanx
          style="verb">constraints</spanx> in that entry MUST be satisfied by the
          Credential.</t>
          <t>Verify status. Unless the Relying Party's policy permits reliance on
          the Trust Mark <spanx style="verb">exp</spanx> alone, the Relying Party
          MUST verify that the Trust Mark is active using the Trust Mark Status
          mechanism (<xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 8.4).</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        A Relying Party that already trusts <spanx
        style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx> natively MAY omit the thumbprint
        comparison in step 6, but MUST still require the Trust Chain to terminate
        at <spanx style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="advertisement" title="Advertisement and Trust Domains">
      <section anchor="adv-ci" title="Advertisement by the Credential Issuer">
        <t>
          The Credential Issuer SHOULD advertise the Trust Mark in the <spanx
          style="verb">trust_marks</spanx> Claim of its Entity Configuration, so
          that Relying Parties can discover it during normal resolution. Each
          array entry contains the <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_type</spanx> and
          the compact serialization of the <spanx
          style="verb">trust-mark+jwt</spanx> (<xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>,
          Section 3).
        </t>
        <t>
          The Trust Mark is signed by the Trust Mark Issuer. Its inclusion in the
          Credential Issuer's self-signed Entity Configuration is solely a means
          of advertisement and carries no trust weight of its own; the Credential
          Issuer's signature over its Entity Configuration does not attest to the
          Trust Mark's content. The Trust Mark's authority derives entirely from
          the Trust Mark Issuer's signature, validated per <xref
          target="rp-processing"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="trust-domains" title="Trust Domains">
        <t>
          Recognition of the Trust Mark Issuer is REQUIRED only within the
          federation(s) whose Relying Parties act on the Trust Mark - that is, the
          Accrediting Federation. The Subject Federation is NOT REQUIRED to
          recognize the Trust Mark Issuer, and its Trust Anchor neither validates
          nor endorses Trust Marks carried in its subordinate Entities' Entity
          Configurations. An unrecognized Trust Mark is ignored by parties that do
          not recognize its Issuer and does not affect the validity of the
          Credential Issuer's Entity Statements or Trust Chain within the Subject
          Federation.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="resolver-behaviour" title="Resolver Behaviour">
        <t>
          A Resolver (<xref target="OpenID.Federation"/>, Section 8.3) returns
          only verified Trust Marks and omits Trust Marks it cannot verify or that
          are not active. A Resolver operating in the Subject Federation therefore
          omits Accrediting-Federation Trust Marks from its resolve responses,
          because it does not recognize the Trust Mark Issuer; this is expected
          and is not an error.
        </t>
        <t>
          Consequently, a Relying Party MUST validate the Trust Mark within a
          trust context in which the Trust Mark Issuer is recognized (that is,
          against the Accrediting Federation Trust Anchor, per <xref
          target="rp-processing"/>). A Relying Party MUST NOT rely on a
          Subject-Federation resolve response having included the Trust Mark in
          its verified set.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="binding" title="Binding the Trust Mark to a Verifiable Credential">
      <t>
        A Credential Issuer MAY embed the Trust Mark in the Verifiable Credentials
        it issues. Embedding is an OPTIONAL convenience that supports offline and
        single-message verification; it does not replace the authoritative source
        (the Credential Issuer's <spanx style="verb">trust_marks</spanx> Claim and
        the Trust Mark Status mechanism). Where current accreditation status is
        required by policy, the Relying Party MUST still perform <xref
        target="rp-processing"/>, step 9.
      </t>

      <section anchor="binding-vcdm" title="W3C Verifiable Credentials Data Model">
        <t>
          For credentials expressed using the W3C Verifiable Credentials Data
          Model 2.0 <xref target="VCDM2"/>, the Trust Mark MUST be conveyed using
          the <spanx style="verb">termsOfUse</spanx> property, which carries
          issuer-asserted policy under which the Credential was issued. This
          profile defines a <spanx style="verb">termsOfUse</spanx> entry with the
          following shape:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="type:">REQUIRED. MUST include the value <spanx
            style="verb">OpenIDFederationTrustMark</spanx>.</t>
            <t hangText="trustMarkType:">REQUIRED. String. MUST equal the embedded
            Trust Mark's <spanx style="verb">trust_mark_type</spanx>.</t>
            <t hangText="trustMark:">REQUIRED. String. The compact serialization
            of the <spanx style="verb">trust-mark+jwt</spanx>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> value and its properties MUST be
          defined by a JSON-LD context that is referenced from the Credential's
          <spanx style="verb">@context</spanx>. A Relying Party processing the
          embedded Trust Mark MUST validate it per <xref target="rp-processing"/>;
          the embedded representation is informative until so validated.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <preamble>Example (non-normative):</preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
"termsOfUse": [
  {
    "type": "OpenIDFederationTrustMark",
    "trustMarkType": "https://accrediting.example/trust-marks/accredited-issuer",
    "trustMark": "<compact trust-mark+jwt>"
  }
]
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The Trust Mark <spanx style="verb">exp</spanx>, if present, SHOULD NOT
          be later than the Credential's own expiry. A Credential Issuer MUST
          define a policy for Credentials already issued at the time an
          accreditation is subsequently revoked.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="binding-other" title="Other Credential Formats">
        <t>
          For Credential formats that do not support <spanx
          style="verb">termsOfUse</spanx> (for example, IETF SD-JWT VC <xref
          target="SD-JWT-VC"/>), a deployment MAY define an equivalent claim
          carrying the same three members. Such a claim SHOULD be present
          unconditionally (not selectively disclosable), since it concerns the
          issuer rather than the subject and a Relying Party requires it to
          evaluate accreditation. The processing rules of <xref
          target="rp-processing"/> apply unchanged.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The security considerations of <xref target="OpenID.Federation"/> apply.
        In addition:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>The Trust Mark Issuer is a cross-federation trust-anchor authority.
          Trusting a Trust Mark means trusting the <spanx
          style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx> and <spanx
          style="verb">subject_trust_anchor_jwks_thumbprints</spanx> it asserts. A
          compromised or negligent Trust Mark Issuer can introduce an
          attacker-controlled Trust Anchor under which forged Credentials resolve.
          Deployments SHOULD constrain the Trust Mark Issuer's authority - for
          example, the Accrediting Federation Trust Anchor MAY publish an
          allow-list of permitted Subject Trust Anchors or Subject Federations,
          and Relying Parties MAY require <spanx
          style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx> to appear on that
          allow-list.</t>
          <t>Identifier binding. A Relying Party MUST bind, in a single
          evaluation, that the Trust Mark <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>, the
          Verifiable Credential issuer identifier, and the subject of the resolved
          Trust Chain are the same Entity, and that this Trust Chain terminates at
          the pinned <spanx style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx>. Omitting
          any leg permits substitution attacks.</t>
          <t>Key pinning. Pinning Subject Trust Anchor keys (<xref
          target="sta-thumbprints"/>), rather than only its identifier, prevents
          the cross-federation bootstrap from depending on transport-layer
          security at the Subject Trust Anchor's endpoints.</t>
          <t>Constraints on dynamically introduced Trust Anchors. Deployment-side
          per-Trust-Anchor constraints (entity type, naming, maximum path length)
          cannot be applied to a Subject Trust Anchor that is not configured at
          the Relying Party. Such constraints MUST instead be expressed in the
          Trust Mark Definition (<xref target="tm-type"/>) and applied per <xref
          target="rp-processing"/>, step 6, so that all Relying Parties scope
          Subject-Federation Trust Chains identically.</t>
          <t>Non-bootstrappable Issuer. The Trust Mark Issuer MUST be recognized
          and resolvable in the Accrediting Federation independently of the Trust
          Mark; a deployment MUST NOT attempt to convey the Trust Mark Issuer's
          trust root inside the Trust Mark.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>
        The privacy considerations of <xref target="OpenID.Federation"/> apply,
        including those for the Trust Mark Status mechanism (Section 19.2), which
        can disclose a Relying Party's interest in a particular subject to the
        Trust Mark Issuer.
      </t>
      <t>
        A Trust Mark under this profile asserts facts about the Credential Issuer,
        not about the Credential subject, and contains no subject personal data;
        embedding it in a Credential (<xref target="binding"/>) introduces no
        additional correlation of the subject.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This profile defines the Trust Mark Claims <spanx
        style="verb">subject_trust_anchor</spanx>, <spanx
        style="verb">subject_trust_anchor_jwks_thumbprints</spanx>, and <spanx
        style="verb">accredited_credentials</spanx> for use within <spanx
        style="verb">trust-mark+jwt</spanx> JWTs, and the W3C VCDM <spanx
        style="verb">termsOfUse</spanx> type <spanx
        style="verb">OpenIDFederationTrustMark</spanx>. Registration of these
        names in the appropriate registries is to be determined.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

      <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner"/>
          <date year="1997" month="March"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174">
        <front>
          <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="Barry Leiba"/>
          <date year="2017" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7519" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7519">
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Token (JWT)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Jones" fullname="Michael B. Jones"/>
          <author initials="J." surname="Bradley" fullname="John Bradley"/>
          <author initials="N." surname="Sakimura" fullname="Nat Sakimura"/>
          <date year="2015" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7519"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7638" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7638">
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Key (JWK) Thumbprint</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Jones" fullname="Michael B. Jones"/>
          <author initials="N." surname="Sakimura" fullname="Nat Sakimura"/>
          <date year="2015" month="September"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7638"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Federation"
                 target="https://openid.net/specs/openid-federation-1_1.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Federation 1.1</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Hedberg" fullname="Roland Hedberg"/>
          <author initials="M.B." surname="Jones" fullname="Michael B. Jones"/>
          <author initials="A." surname="Solberg" fullname="Andreas Solberg"/>
          <author initials="J." surname="Bradley" fullname="John Bradley"/>
          <author initials="G." surname="De Marco" fullname="Giuseppe De Marco"/>
          <author initials="V." surname="Dzhuvinov" fullname="Vladimir Dzhuvinov"/>
          <date year="2026" month="May"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="VCDM2"
                 target="https://www.w3.org/TR/vc-data-model-2.0/">
        <front>
          <title>Verifiable Credentials Data Model v2.0</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Sporny" fullname="Manu Sporny"/>
          <author initials="D." surname="Longley" fullname="Dave Longley"/>
          <author initials="D." surname="Chadwick" fullname="David Chadwick"/>
          <date year="2025" month="May"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="SD-JWT-VC"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-oauth-sd-jwt-vc/">
        <front>
          <title>SD-JWT-based Verifiable Credentials (SD-JWT VC)</title>
          <author initials="O." surname="Terbu" fullname="Oliver Terbu"/>
          <author initials="D." surname="Fett" fullname="Daniel Fett"/>
          <author initials="B." surname="Campbell" fullname="Brian Campbell"/>
          <date year="2025"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC8725" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8725">
        <front>
          <title>JSON Web Token Best Current Practices</title>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Sheffer" fullname="Yaron Sheffer"/>
          <author initials="D." surname="Hardt" fullname="Dick Hardt"/>
          <author initials="M." surname="Jones" fullname="Michael B. Jones"/>
          <date year="2020" month="February"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="225"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8725"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="example" title="Non-Normative Example: Education and Healthcare">
      <t>
        This appendix instantiates the profile for a vocational-education
        Credential Issuer accredited for healthcare use across two federations.
        All identifiers are fictional and use the <spanx
        style="verb">.example</spanx> reserved domain.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Accrediting Federation Trust Anchor (Trust Mark Owner):
          https://trust-anchor.healthcare-federation.example</t>
          <t>Trust Mark Issuer (accreditation authority):
          https://accreditation-council.healthcare-federation.example</t>
          <t>Subject Federation Trust Anchor:
          https://trust-anchor.education-federation.example</t>
          <t>Credential Issuer (Leaf Entity in the Subject Federation):
          https://riverside-college.education-federation.example</t>
          <t>Trust Mark type:
          https://healthcare-federation.example/trust-marks/accredited-care-programme-issuer</t>
          <t>Credential type (governed externally):
          https://diploma-registry.example/vct/vocational-diploma</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <figure>
        <preamble>Trust Mark (typ: trust-mark+jwt):</preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "iss": "https://accreditation-council.healthcare-federation.example",
  "sub": "https://riverside-college.education-federation.example",
  "trust_mark_type":
    "https://healthcare-federation.example/trust-marks/accredited-care-programme-issuer",
  "iat": 1718000000,
  "exp": 1749536000,
  "ref": "https://healthcare-federation.example/trust-marks/.../criteria",
  "delegation": "<trust-mark-delegation+jwt>",
  "subject_trust_anchor": "https://trust-anchor.education-federation.example",
  "subject_trust_anchor_jwks_thumbprints": [
    "NzbLsXh8uDCcd-6MNwXF4W_7noWXFZAfHkxZsRGC9Xs"
  ],
  "accredited_credentials": [
    {
      "format": "dc+sd-jwt",
      "vct": "https://diploma-registry.example/vct/vocational-diploma",
      "constraints": {
        "qualification": {
          "framework": "national-qualifications-framework",
          "code": "nursing-level-4"
        }
      }
    }
  ]
}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <preamble>AF Trust Anchor Entity Configuration (excerpt):</preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "trust_mark_issuers": {
    "https://healthcare-federation.example/trust-marks/accredited-care-programme-issuer": [
      "https://accreditation-council.healthcare-federation.example"
    ]
  },
  "trust_mark_owners": {
    "https://healthcare-federation.example/trust-marks/accredited-care-programme-issuer": {
      "sub": "https://trust-anchor.healthcare-federation.example",
      "jwks": { "keys": [ { "kty": "..." } ] }
    }
  }
}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <preamble>Credential Issuer Entity Configuration (excerpt):</preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "iss": "https://riverside-college.education-federation.example",
  "sub": "https://riverside-college.education-federation.example",
  "trust_marks": [
    {
      "trust_mark_type":
        "https://healthcare-federation.example/trust-marks/accredited-care-programme-issuer",
      "trust_mark": "<compact trust-mark+jwt>"
    }
  ]
}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <preamble>W3C VCDM credential with embedded Trust Mark (excerpt):</preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "@context": [
    "https://www.w3.org/ns/credentials/v2",
    "https://healthcare-federation.example/contexts/trust-mark-v1"
  ],
  "type": ["VerifiableCredential", "VocationalDiploma"],
  "issuer": "https://riverside-college.education-federation.example",
  "credentialSubject": {
    "qualification": {
      "framework": "national-qualifications-framework",
      "code": "nursing-level-4"
    }
  },
  "termsOfUse": [
    {
      "type": "OpenIDFederationTrustMark",
      "trustMarkType":
        "https://healthcare-federation.example/trust-marks/accredited-care-programme-issuer",
      "trustMark": "<compact trust-mark+jwt>"
    }
  ]
}
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notices" title="Notices">
      <t>
        This is a non-normative working document created during design
        discussion. It is not an OpenID Foundation specification and has not been
        adopted by any working group. It profiles OpenID Federation and reuses the
        OpenID Foundation document template solely for authoring convenience.
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
